Okay. Rows and columns and CSS grid.
حسنًا. لنتحدث عن الصفوف والأعمدة وشبكة CSS.
The longest journey begins with the first step.
تذكروا مشوار الألف ميل يبدأ بخطوة.
So here we have set up a container element with display grid.
لاحظوا، ضبطنا  خاصية عرض عنصر الحاوية على شبكة.
Then in our HTML we have three divs with a class box inside of our container.
وفي برمجة HTML، لدينا ثلاثة أقسام (div) من فئة (class) مربع داخل الحاوية.
You can see that CSS grid right out of
يمكن رؤية شبكة CSS
the box comes with some distribution and alignment.
والمربعات تظهر موزعة ووفق محاذاة محددة.
We have box one, box two,
لدينا المربع واحد، المربع اثنان،
box three here in one column along three rows.
المربع ثلاثة، تتوزع في عمود واحد وثلاثة صفوف.
Before we do anything else let's look at the grid gap quickly.
قبل أن نبدأ، لننظر إلى فراغ الشبكة سريعًا.
Again the grid gap is what allows you to put
خاصية فراغ الشبكة تتيح لنا تخصيص
more or less space between each element in a grid.
مسافة أكبر أو أقل بين كل عنصرين في الشبكة.
So right now these elements have 50 px in between them each.
يبلغ الفراغ بين كل عنصر والآخر هنا 50 بيكسل.
But for example if we did a 150 pixels,
ولكن لو عدّلناها إلى 150 بيكسل مثلًا،
you can see that they spread out much further.
نلاحظ أنها ستبتعد عن بعضها بمسافة أكبر.
If we did 15 pixels,
وإذا عدّلناها إلى 15 بيكسل،
they become much closer together.
ستقترب العناصر من بعضها البعض أكثر.
These are called the gutters inside the tracks.
تسمى الهوامش داخل المسارات.
Tracks are what setup rows and columns,
المسارات هي ما يحدد الأعمدة والصفوف،
and gutters are the space in between.
والهوامش هي المسافات فيما بينها.
So what if instead of having one column with three rows,
ماذا لو أردنا تحويل عمود واحد وثلاثة صفوف،
what if we actually wanted to have three columns.
إلى ثلاثة أعمدة؟
Inside of our container div,
نذهب إلى قسم الحاوية (div)
we could use the grid template columns property and then we could set three columns.
ونستعمل خاصية أعمدة قالب الشبكة وننشئ ثلاثة أعمدة.
The way that you do that is simply by entering three values.
وذلك عن طريق إدخال ثلاثة قيم.
So 300 Px is the first column,
هذه 300 بيكسل للعمود الأول،
300 Px is the second column and let's make the third column a little shorter,
و300 بيكسل للعمود الثاني، وليكن العمود الثالث أقصر قليلًا،
we'll say 200 pixels.
200 بيكسل مثلًا.
So now we can see that we have three elements,
أصبح لدينا ثلاثة عناصر،
three columns and they are outside of our grid a little bit,
ثلاثة أعمدة، ولكنها تمتد خارج الشبكة قليلًا،
and that's because our width of our grid is less than the total of the columns.
وذلك لأن عرض الشبكة أقل من العرض الكلي للأعمدة.
To fix that we can easily just increase the width of our grid.
لتصحيح ذلك، بوسعنا زيادة عرض الشبكة.
For now I'll make it 100 percent.
سأجعلها 100 بالمائة.
So now we can see our grid is plenty wide and we
نلاحظ أن الشبكة واسعة بما يكفي،
have three elements each of them here in columns.
ولدينا ثلاثة عناصر، كل منها هنا في عمود.
Another thing we could do is change the grid template rows.
من الأمور الأخرى التي يمكننا فعلها، استخدام خاصية الصفوف في قالب الشبكة.
Here we can see we've set up three rows,
أصبح لدينا ثلاثة صفوف،
so there's one column in the middle and each of
هذا عمود واحد في الوسط
these boxes has taken on the height of the row we set.
وقد تغيرت أبعاد المربعات بناء على ارتفاع الصف الذي قمنا بضبطه.
So the first box is 300 pixels,
العنصر الأول 300 بيكسل،
the second box smaller is 250 pixels and the third box is large, 600 pixels.
العنصر الثاني أصغر، بواقع 250 بيكسل، والثالث أكبر بارتفاع 600 بيكسل.
That is easy to change.
من السهل تغيير ذلك.
For instance if we wanted our first row to be much
فمثلًا، إذا أردنا أن يكون الصف الأول أكبر
bigger and our last row to be much smaller we could simply change the entries.
بكثير والصف الأخير أصغر بكثير، يمكننا تغيير القيم ببساطة.
So now the first row is 600 pixels which means
أصبح ارتفاع الصف الأول 600 بيكسل، مما يعني
that the first box in our first row will be 600 pixels.
أن بعد العنصر الأول في الصف الأول سيكون 600 بيكسل.
The second box is 250,
العنصر الثاني 250،
and then our third box is tiny, it's 60 pixels.
والعنصر الثالث صغير جدًا، ارتفاعه 60 بيكسل.
Now you might think why would a 60 pixel row be necessary?
قد تتساءلون هل يلزمنا صف ارتفاعه 60 بيكسل؟
But the truth is think about the web.
للإجابة، ينبغي أن نفكر بصفحة الويب.
Say footers for example.
مثل تذييل الصفحة.
Every website has at least one bar on the bottom line that's really small,
يحتوي كل موقع إلكتروني على شريط واحد على الأقل في الجزء السفلي منه، يكون صغيرًا جدًا.
and this is a great way to set that up.
وهذه طريقة ممتازة لضبطه.
By setting up our rows like this you can create
عند ضبط الصفوف بهذه الطريقة، يمكن إنشاء
content tracks that makes sense for the type of content that you make.
مسارات المحتوى المناسبة لنوع المحتوى الذي تقدمه.
That's just a little bit what you can do with
كانت هذه نبذة بسيطة عما يمكن فعله
grid template rows and grid template columns.
باستخدام خاصيتي صفوف قالب الشبكة وأعمدة قالب الشبكة.
Coming up we're going to learn how to put them together
في الدروس التالية سنتعرف إلى كيفية استخدامهما معًا
to create grid areas which allow you to setup
لإنشاء مساحات الشبكة التي تتيح ضبط
columns and rows to create
الأعمدة والصفوف لإنشاء
a whole system that you can then use to put your elements into.
نظام كامل يمكنك استخدامه لوضع العناصر فيه.